Register of the European subject collection, 1890-2009
Hoover Institution Archives
European subject collection,
1890-2009
XX758
16 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 phonotape cassette (6.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issues, proclamations, reports, certificates, correspondence, election campaign literature, video tapes, and memorabilia, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century European history and politics, and especially to the socialist movement in Europe between the two world wars, post-World War II efforts to promote European cooperation and unity, and elections to the European Parliament.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives. An increment was added in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issues, proclamations, reports, certificates, correspondence, election campaign literature, video tapes, and memorabilia, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century European history and politics, and especially to the socialist movement in Europe between the two world wars, post-World War II efforts to promote European cooperation and unity, and elections to the European Parliament.
Indexing Terms
Socialism--Europe; Europe--History--20th century; Europe--Politics and government--20th century; Elections--Europe; European cooperation; European federation; European Parliament; Phonotapes; Videotapes
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1902-1994. (Box 1-14)
  Bulletins, pamphlets, serial issues, maps and other printed matter relating to miscellaneous aspects of European political, social and cultural life.
Container List
SEE CARD CATALOG FOR INCREMENTS THAT MAY HAVE BEEN RECEIVED AFTER DEC. 1994
- SUBJECT FILE, 1902-1994
  - General (Box 1.)
    - Miscellaneous. Bulletins, pamphlets, serial issues, maps, and printed matter, 1902-1981, relating to miscellaneous aspects of various European countries. In English, French, German, Czech, and Spanish Anti-communist movements. Pamphlet issued by the Bureau Permanent de l'Entente Internationale contre la IIIe Internationale, entitled "Neuf ans de lutte contre le bolchevisme," 1933. In French
    - Central and Eastern Europe
      - General. Reprint of a speech by Hubert Ripka delivered on 28 April 1955 and relating to the status of Central and Eastern Europe before the Four Powers Conference. In French
      - Human rights. Pamphlet, 1966, published by the Assembly of Captive European Nations and relating to human rights violations in Central and Eastern Europe
      - Oder-Neisse-Line. Reprint of a legal study by Herbert Kraus, 1954, relating to the history of the Oder- Neisse-Line. In German
    - European civilization. Pamphlet by Jean Kanapa entitled "L'Etat de siege; voila le dernier mot de votre civilisation!" 1950? relating to post World War II European politics
    - European Community
      - Booklet, 1986, relating to the 25th anniversary of the European Social Charter
      - Circular issued by the German Information Center in New York, 1988, relating to the Unified Market of 1992
      - Election material for the parliamentary elections
        - June 1984
          - General
          - France (Box 2.)
          - Germany
          - Great Britain (Box 3.)
          - Italy
          - Results
        - June 1989
          - General
          - France
          - Germany
          - Great Britain
          - Italy
        - June 1994 (Box 11.)
          - General
          - Belgium
          - Denmark
          - France
          - Germany
          - Germany (Box 12.)
          - Germany (Box 13.)
          - Great Britain
          - Greece
          - Italy
          - Luxemburg (Box 14.)
          - Netherlands
          - Portugal
          - Spain
      - Maastricht Treaty. Brochures, flyers, leaflets, newsletters, and magazine and newspaper issues relating to the French referendum of October 15, 1992, on the Maastricht Treaty on European unification. Includes the text of the treaty as distributed to the French voters. In French (Box 3.)
    - International Commission Against Concentration Camp Practices, Brussels. Report, 1950 (Box 4.)
    - North Atlantic Treaty Organization. Two copies of the Declaration of Paris, adopted in Paris by the Atlantic Convention of NATO Nations on January 19, 1962; and a flyer describing the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe (SHAPE), n.d. (in English)
    - Political parties. Transnational Radical Party, 1993
    - Security. Pamphlets, newsletters, and a Rand Corporation study, 1988-1990, relating to the future of European security, the INF treaty, and the Warsaw Pact
    - Socialism. Reports, leaflets, pamphlets, and newspaper issues, l923-l946, relating to the 3rd and 4th Congresses of the Labour and Socialist International, activities of socialist parties and their social, cultural and labor affiliates in Germany, Austria, and Czechoslovakia in the interwar period, and activities of Czech socialists in England during World War II (Box 5-9.)
    - Socialist youth. Newsletters of the World Federation of Democratic Youth and of the International Committee of the Children's and Adolescents' Movements, attached to the WFDY, 1984-1985; and of International Union of Students, 1978 (Box 10.)
    - Spaak, Paul-Henri. Reprint of an article by Andri Visson published in The American Mercury, November 1946
  - Netherlands (Box 10.)
    - Booklet, 1986, relating to the Dutch language
    - Pamphlets and serial issues, 1978-1984, relating to the disarmament movement in the Netherlands. In Dutch
  - Scandinavia. Serial issues, proceedings of congresses, and underground literature, l890-l949, relating to politics, socialism, and the peace movement in Scandinavia. In Swedish and Danish
- Incremental Materials (Box 15-17)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu